General Manuscripts Collection, 1765-2016: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
General Manuscripts Collection
1765-2016
1836-2016
AC001
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections. Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library. Princeton University Archives. 65 Olden Street Princeton, New Jersey 08540 USA
1.25 linear feet 3 boxes
Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library.
The General Manuscripts Collection consists of manuscripts and small collections of papers and records which are related in some way to the history of Princeton University. While most documents in the General Manuscripts collection were produced by alumni or student organizations, there are several documents produced by trustees, faculty, and other members of the University community.
The General Manuscripts Collection consists of individual manuscripts and small collections of papers and records which are related in some way to the history, students, and alumni of Princeton University. The vast majority of the documents in the General Manuscripts collection were produced by alumni, although there are several exceptions such as trustees or other members of the University community.
Notes within the contents list provide further details on the contents of individual folders.
Documents within the General Manuscripts Collection are arranged alphabetically by the name of the individual or organization that authored or created them.
Collection is open for research use.
The documents which comprise the General Manuscripts Collection have been collected by the Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library over a span of several years, primarily beginning in the 1990s. Whenever possible, accession numbers have been included with folder descriptions.
No information on appraisal is available.
Additions are made to the General Manuscripts Collection when materials which fit the scope of the collection are accessioned by the Library.
As the General Manuscripts collection touches upon such a broad range of subject, the Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library holds numerous collections which are related to it in some way. These include the Student Writings and Correspondence Collection, the Historic Subject Files, the Princetoniana Collection, and the Scrapbook and Autograph Book Collections. The Library also holds undergraduate alumni files for many of the authors of these materials.
The manuscripts and collections which comprise the General Manuscripts Collection have all been cataloged individually, and are searchable through the Princeton University Library's online catalog. The information presented in this finding aid duplicates that found in the online catalog records.
Princeton University -- Student life.; Princeton University -- Students -- 19th century.; Princeton University -- Students -- 20th century.; Education, Higher; Correspondence.; Princeton University
- C.H. Andrews Speech "On National Ingratitude", 1820; AR.2016.136; 1 folder (Box 3)
  Speech given by C.H. Andrews titled "On National Ingratitude" at Nassau Hall on February 18, 1820 on the topic of a lack of gratitude for the country's veterans.
- Letter of A. Frank McFadden to the Princeton University Athletic Association, 1883 April 14; AR.2001.042; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
  The Athletic Association is the organization which oversees the administration of Princeton University's athletic programs.
  Consists of one letter containing an invitation for participation in the spring sports of the Philadelphia Fencing and Sparring Club/
- Lafayette Butler Newsletters, 1905-1907; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 2 to 3)
  Lafayette Butler was a member of the Princeton Class of 1908.
  Contains copies of The Eagle, a campus newsletter written by Lafayette Butler, Class of 1908.
- James Campbell Davis Letter to David B. Smith, 1848 April 26; AR.1992.041; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
  James Campbell Davis was a member of the Princeton University Class of 1849
  One letter from James Campbell Davis to David B. Smith concerning the upcoming Presidential election of 1848 and other current affairs.
- Thomas H. English Papers Relating to Morris H. Croll, 1917-1965; AR.1993.027; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
  (Correspondence between Thomas H. English, Class of 1918 and English Professor Morris H. Croll, as well as papers regarding the posthumous printing of Croll's work.)
- Reminiscences of a Trustee, 1913; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Wilson Farrand was an active trustee of Princeton University during the early part 20th century.
  Consists of typed reminiscences of Princeton University trustee Wilson Farrand describing the dispute between then-president Woodrow Wilson and Andrew Fleming West regarding the location of the proposed graduate school. Also included is a retelling of Senator James Smith, Jr.'s nomination of Woodrow Wilson for the office of governor of New Jersey in 1910.
- Carole Grayson Student Teaching Journal, 1974; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Carole Grayson was a member of the Princeton University Class of 1974.
  Consists of the journal kept by Carole Grayson documenting her experiences as a student teacher at Princeton High School.
- Minute Book, 1913-1915; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
  The Hour-Glass Society was a short lived organization at Princeton University's Graduate College dedicated to the discussion of questions of a philosophical, ethical, or religious nature. The Society held regular Sunday evening meetings at which professors or other guest speakers would lecture on a chosen topic. Topics ranged from "the relation of reason to faith" to "what is sin?"
  Consists of one book of meeting minutes documenting the organization and activities of the Hour-Glass Society. Mentioned in the entries are the lecture topic of given meetings as well as the speaker and the number of attendees.
- Insurance Policy on the Life of Benedict Jaeger, 1840; AR.2016.135; 1 folder (Box 3)
  Benedict Jaeger was a professor of Germanic Languages and Literature.
  Insurance policy taken out by Professors John Maclean, Albert Dod, and Joseph Henry on the life of Jaeger for four hundred dollars.
- Edward MacMillan Letters, 1917-1919; AR.2003.089; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Edward Allen MacMillan was a member of Princeton's Class of 1918. He served in France with the American Expeditionary Force in World War I, and then returned to the campus as the head of Grounds and Buildings. MacMillan Hall was so named in recognition of his service to the University.
  Consists of 19 letters written by Edward MacMillan to the Kopp family of Princeton from the front lines in France during World War I. In the letters MacMillan discusses the trials of warfare as well as lighter matters, such as news of fellow Princetonians and regimental baseball games.
- Elementary Plates in Mechanical Drawing, 1890; AR.1998.076; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Gilbert MacMillan was a member of the Princeton Class of 1891.
  Book of numbered and colored mechanical drawings produced by Gilbert MacMillan while an undergraduate.
- Nassau Hall, "Burning of Nassau Hall", 1855; AR.2000.116; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
  A detailed account of the 1855 fire which consumed Nassau Hall, penned by an unknown eyewitness.
- Minute and Subscription Books, 1836-1842; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
  The Nassau Hall Missionary Society was an organization formed in 1836 by students and faculty of the College of New Jersey for the purpose of collecting donations for foreign missions. The first elected leader of the organization was President James Carnahan, and in its first year the group raised 78 dollars for charity. As the records cease after 1842, the eventual fate of the Nassau Hall Missionary Society is unclear.
  Consists of two volumes containing the meeting minutes and the financial accounts of the Nassau Hall Missionary Society.
- Henry Fairfield Osborn Papers, 1857-1935; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  Henry Fairfield Osborn was a member of the Princeton class of 1877, one of the earliest graduates of the School of Science. He returned to Princeton in 1883 after graduate study as a professor of comparative anatomy, where he distinguished himself as one of the foremost scholars in biology and paleontology in America. During this time Osborn also assisted in the administration of the college, balancing accounts and reorganizing the athletics program.
  Consists of numerous documents relating to the financial accounts of the College of New Jersey (later Princeton University) at the end of the 19th century. While there are some general reports of the treasurer present in the collection, most of the records directly relate to Henry Fairfield Osborn's efforts to fund the redevelopment of the college’s athletic fields and facilities.
- Princeton Postcards, 1996; AR.1997.049; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Kenneth R. Perry is a member of the Princeton Class of 1950.
  A set of 52 postcards sent by R. Kenneth Perry to Princeton President Harold Shapiro from various towns and locations named Princeton throughout the United States.
- Correspondence Between Gerald H. Rosen '55 *59 and Professor John A. Wheeler, 1979-1989; AR.2012.070; portion of 1 box (Box 3)
  Correspondence Between Gerald H. Rosen '55 *59 and Professor John A. Wheeler primarily consisting of letters of thanks from Rosen to Wheeler for having provided him letters of recommendation.
- Stevens Family Journal, 1898-1912; AR.2009.002; portion of 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Weld Merrick Stevens and his brother Laurance Stevens were members of the Princeton Class of 1904.
  Consists of one journal kept by the family of Weld Merrick and Laurance Stevens '04. The journal, written in many hands, describes weather, social events, outings, and family genealogy.
- Receipt for Expenses of a Woodworker, Signed by Richard Stockton as Trustee of College of New Jersey, 1765; AR.2010.071; 1 box (Box 3)
  Richard Stockton, Class of 1748, served as a trustee of the College from 1757-1781. Stockton was a signer of the Declaration of Independence.
  The receipt is for the expenses of woodworker Caleb Bruen. He lists charges for paying and boarding his apprentice, a "mantell tree," and a door frame, totaling 3 pounds. It is signed by Stockton and Judge John Berrien, a judge of the Supreme Court of New Jersey and fellow trustee.
- Diary of John M. Van Dyke, Class of 1872, 1888-1889; AR.2016.134; 1 folder (Box 3)
- Drawing of East College, 1868; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
  George W. Van Wagenen was a member of the Princeton Class of 1868.
  Consists of a pencil on paper sketch labeled "Our Room - East College" depicting the artist's dorm room and furnishings.
- Theodore Von Laue Letters, 1942-1943; AR.2006.067; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Theodore H. Von Laue was a member of the Princeton University Graduate School class of 1939. Upon the entrance of the United States into the Second World War, Von Laue began a newsletter for the purpose of distributing news about the activities of his fellow graduate students, particularly those in the Department of History.
  Consists of 36 letters and postcards sent to Theodore Von Laue by Princeton graduate students serving in the armed forces during the early years of American involvement in the Second World War, which generally discuss military life and current events. Also included are four issues of Von Laue's informal newsletter, written to keep the history students in the service up to date on each other's locations as well as apprised of emerging trends in the study of history.
- Charles McAlpin, Certificate as life member of American National Red Cross, 1916 March 10; AR.2010.157; 1 item (Cabinet 4, Drawer 5)
  Signed by Woodrow Wilson
- "Breakfast in Princeton, USA: A Year-Long Odyssey--1996", 2016; AR.2016.096; portion of 1 box (Box 3)
  Book, signed by the author, published by Kenneth Perry '1950 documenting road trips he and his wife took to every town in the United States named Princeton. Each stop along the journey includes photographs and historical information about each location.
- Robert Montgomery Brown '1930 Guest Book, News Clippings and Photographs, 1928-1930; AR.2013.144; portion of 1 box (Box 3)
  This folder contains a guest book of signatures for Robert Montgomery Brown's dormitory room, #6 Middle Dod, as well as news clippings, both loose and glued into the guest book, and news photographs of Brown and his room. Robert Montgomery Brown, Class of 1930, attracted press attention for his domestic "Rube Goldberg" contraptions such as the alarm clock that would trigger the mechanics to boil an egg.